this is the first rebel wisdom podcast
and we're basically my name's David
fuller I'm Alexander Boehner and
together we are rebel wisdom and I
assume that most people who watch this
will be subscribers and they'll have
seen some of the stuff that we've been
putting out the Jordan Peters and stuff
and whatever so the idea is to give a
little bit of background about what the
rebel wisdom project is where we're
going and yeah what the kind of what the
thought behind it is so even though this
is addressed at you I'm gonna keep
looking at hell even though that's a
real even that Ali knows everything like
Italian so my background I used to work
for Channel four News
I've been a journalist for about 15
years left started doing documentaries
and during that time I've also done a
lot of I studied philosophy at
University and have always been
interested in big ideas and also
personal growth work lots of shadow work
lots of which is the stuff that really
kind of drew me to Jordan Peterson a
couple of years ago a year or so ago and
all through that time I've also been
kind of thinking about how to get some
of these more interesting slightly
esoteric subjects onto mainstream media
and realizing it's very difficult to get
these in because there's there's there's
gatekeepers there's a huge resistance
especially to stuff that sort of is in
you might call spiritual or religious or
there's a kind of materialist skepticism
and I think that is a real yes it's a
real barrier and through rebel wisdom
aim is to bring a deeper sense of yeah
just a much deeper conversation than the
one that we're really seeing in the
mainstream media at the moment which
sort of ties into the whole intellectual
dark web thing and a lot of the films
and stuff that we've done and stuff we
are going to cover so what you tell me
about your background stuff yes stuff
you don't know yes so I'm a writer and
I'm also quite involved in the
psychedelic community so I help organize
a conference that happens every two
years called breaking convention about a
thousand really interesting mix of
neuroscientists all the way to really
hardcore hippies kind of all coming
together to discuss psychedelic research
and culture and also for the last five
or six years I've been teaching
non-religious meditation through an
organization I set up in London
so far we've put out I'd know 1015 bits
of content on the rebel wisdom YouTube
channel we've got a medium channel we're
putting out some blogs and so far one
writer Andrew Sweeney he's been doing
some really good stuff for us and so far
I think we've done I mean I we did
pretty well with the Jordan Peterson
stuff I mean I remember discovering
Jordan Peterson last June and just
immediately thinking this is the thing
that is needed right now
this is about the reinterment of the
world the assimilation of spirituality
the assimilation of religion this is
this is the thing and I was kind of
obsessed like digesting listening to all
of his stuff and then pitched an
interview to him and was lucky enough to
get an interview with him in October
that we then put out as the truth in the
time of chaos documentary in in January
at exactly the time that ironically he
then kind of shot to fame with an
interview with my ex colleague Kathy
Newman on Channel 4 News
when a lot of what I had gone to talk to
Jordan Peterson about was synchronicity
and it was just uncanny that's when the
synchronicity stopped that's right
that's right that's when things start to
line up yeah and the more you're in that
space the more they line up yeah and so
the question is if you're like really in
that space
how much do things line up all of this
was happening and I I wondered what I
was gonna make what to make of this and
for quite a while I was thinking well I
have this kind of link to to Kathy and I
have some kind of link to Jordan so what
I need to do is the am and get them to
go and do the second interview that I
thought was necessary and so for a while
I was doing that
kind of trying to do stuff behind the
scenes and then it was clear that Cathy
wasn't interested Channel four weren't
interested
so Channel four News sorry weren't
interested so in the end I thought well
I came and then it came to me okay I
should make a documentary glitching the
matrix which then was a way of like just
downloading all the stuff that I've been
thinking about for quite a while and
especially since the election of Trump
about kind of the the shadow side of
liberalism and all of the the blind
spots of liberalism so glitching the
matrix was kind of a the title of it and
it all it was it came from a very from a
real flow state of like being really a
line and feeling like okay this is what
I meant to be doing which is the essence
of kind of synchronicity and the essence
of Jordan Peterson's deeper meaning is
you know when you're aligned at the
right place and then your sense of
meaning tells you what to do so this and
I think the impact that it's had so far
which has been pretty great like the
response has been really great and I'm
quite proud of it as a piece of work has
shown that it's something that that
people really wanted and I met a lot of
people at the Jordan Peterson event last
night who were saying you came up to me
and shook my hand and said wow this is
really interesting it really showed me
it kind of opened my eyes to a lot of
what was going on so I'm quite proud of
that and really keen that we keep going
so you could say why why the obsession
with Jordan Pederson and for me it's
it's not really about Jordan Peterson
Jordan Pederson is kind of the messenger
and is an amazing advocate for something
that we've forgotten and that for me is
the deep story of Western culture and he
is embodying that deep story of Western
culture in his performances he's talking
about aligning yourself with the truth
the logos and I think he's often
misconstrued by people who can't get
past the politics or have a reactivity
to him but to me he is doing nothing
less than channeling and fully
articulating the deep story of Western
culture for the first
and well certainly for the first time in
the Internet age you could argue that
Young was doing the same thing back in
the in the 50s and that there are people
who come along and do this at times in
the past but effectively saying we
already know a lot of the answers we
already know the way to live it's
embodied interaction that's embodied in
mythologies embodied in our religions
it's embodied and all of these things
look at this piece of art what is it
saying we represented it in art we
represented it in all these ways and now
we can fully articulate it tie into
neuroscience tie into and that it's a
it's an epic epic project and so I get
accused and it's very easy to say well
you're obsessed with Jordan Peterson
you're a fanboy and all that stuff and
but for me the message that he's
bringing forward is that deep it's that
deep and therefore I want to continue to
use his thought as a lens to link into
other great thinkers like we just put
out an interview with Rupert Sheldrake
who I think is an amazing rebellious
thinker he's been doing this stuff for a
long time and I want to also continue to
kind of expand that into other into
other thinkers make the conscious link
to to this sort of deeper worldview and
help yeah just bring out great
bring out great content really what do
you make of Jordan Peterson it took you
a little bit longer maybe to get into it
yeah it did I mean I'm thinking back to
to like maybe this time last year and I
think one of the first things we started
talking about was Wilbur's Trump and a
post truth world so Ken Wilber
yeah Ken Wilber who kind of yeah was the
driving force or is behind integral
studies which is to cut a long story
short and we are gonna be releasing a
lot of interviews with integral thinkers
coming up so but this idea of trying to
see reality as fully as possible and
it's really it's a really deep model it
was one of the first things that really
got me into wanting to integrate my
shadow and really see the importance of
that and seeing
we're the Eastern traditions couldn't
comment on the Western traditions and
vice versa and quite a big model so
after Trump was elected he wrote a great
piece where he pointed out that part of
the part of the reason if not the reason
is because the leading edge of culture
had been what in their model they
defined as green which is the kind of
pluralistic relative progressive you you
could say and that it can become kind of
the leading edge of our arts and our
assumptions and kind of a leading edge
of culture however to cut a long story
short it's not nearly as inclusive as it
thinks it is so it's got a shadow it
doesn't want to look at its own and a
performative contradictions yes so Green
basically is inclusivity
it's what fuels civil rights it's what
fuels so the wave of kind of equality of
the 60s and 70s but then it became
corrupt yeah because it didn't realize
it was a tribalism yeah and that's a
really key thing with it is that it's a
really important stage of development so
that so all of integral Studies is
really based around not throwing out the
baby with the bathwater it's a real it's
a model that says yes and just like when
you become nine years old you don't kill
your five-year-old self you grow and you
and your five year old self is you know
your experiences are all there they're
recontextualized so yeah that was
exactly it is that Green has become
toxic effectively and you know to almost
a very tribal degree of you know will be
inclusive as long as you're as inclusive
as us otherwise you are a deplorable so
it's really what Hillary Clinton said so
that really was a one of the most
interesting things I read and resonated
with me the most and then it took me a
while to get into Jordan Peterson you
know I was interested but it just took
well it takes a while to really get to
watch enough of this stuff because it's
complex it's not an easy it's not an
easily understood thing it takes time to
really wrestle with and get into yeah
and then then I think there's two things
with him that I think are really
important that I really see is that a
he's very hard to categorize and he is
part of if not the main driving force
now in getting green to look at his own
shadow you know and he's bringing up
some of what integral studies they would
call the kind of the the levels before
that the traditionalism all of that you
know clean your room and really kind of
connecting with certainty and that and
then that's the key thing it's truth and
more than that he's sort of channeling a
kind of traditionalist knowledge that
has been forgotten by the relativistic
and postmodern world basically and
that's why we would and we were so
thirsty for it and that's where his
color of success has come from yeah
definitely I think and I think there's
this there's a huge power in that but
there's a need for it it's it's there's
a deep need for it and I've always had a
problem with post-modernism ever since I
would I studied English universe I
studied English in University and a
postmodern writing is is really bad you
know because it doesn't follow the
mythic journey you know doesn't follow
the mono myth it kind of subvert and it
can be interesting it's kind of an
intellectual masturbation but in general
I thought this is smoke and mirrors you
know this is not tapping into the depths
of the psyche and everyone knows
everyone when you read a story whether
you're five years old or whether you're
90 years old it resonates with you
because but that's Joseph Campbell's
insight into the mono myth it's because
the story isn't about what you're
reading it's about your own inner
personal journey which is shared
collectively it's about the process of
an individual going from a state of a
lower level of awareness to a state of
more awareness so you know frodo starts
in the Shire and he's a bit of a wimp
and he you know he likes to stay home
then he gets a call to adventure then it
goes in a journey and when he returned
you know he encounters his own darkness
you know Luke Skywalker's the perfect
example when he's with Yoda he
encounters Darth Vader or a vision of
him it cuts off his head with a
lightsaber and it's his own face behind
the mask you know it's it's about as
symbolic as it gets so all of the
stories that we really really like to
watch follow a mythic journey and
post-modernism through literature often
doesn't or subvert it in some way and
you know it's all about kind of playing
with it
which is fine you know that's a literary
thing but when when the values of that
are applied to how people actually live
their lives it's insane it's it's what
can we work all day
it creates narcissism but it also
creates what he called a perspectival
madness because it everything is
relative and there's no truth and
there's no certainty you you go mad
we're human beings we we need it and
we'll finally so that becomes a
certainty the eighth pursuit of a
prospective or madness as well is I'm
certain there's no truth like oh so
that's the truth is it it's I've always
been yeah that's always being an
argument I feel that has come up again
and again and again and again like when
I'm talking to someone it's like yeah
well there is no truth it's like though
but hang on yeah and it becomes kind of
completely yo just disappear down the
rabbit hole yeah the other it's
interesting as well the the reactivity
to Peterson because the other thing
about integral theory that's really good
and I think is also informing a lot of
what we're interested in and doing is
the idea of yes end so integral theory
is always yes and so it's it's a process
of integrating and moving beyond and
integrating and moving beyond and I do
think that there is almost certainly a
deeper resolution than Dan Peterson by
Peterson is bringing forward something
something timeless and eternal and
something that has to be integrated
before we move forward but I think there
is a part that we can move forward and I
think Peterson himself is actually
trying to do that I mean you get a sense
when he's talking on stage he's thinking
and he's genuinely trying to work out
where he's wrong where he can get better
and more and and and I think he's he's
probably now that he's kind of reached a
level ii he's reached is having
conversations with other thinkers on a
similar level to him that are going to
probably develop his thought even
further and I would say the only level I
often challenged by people is like where
you know you're never critical at
Peterson like well that's because most
of the criticisms are nonsense and they
show more about you than they do about
him like their reactivity but I think
the one criticism I think is valid is
one that he's
now a thinker on the world stage he's
not he's not in student politics anymore
and I think there's a certain reactivity
to to student politics that that I think
comes across as a sort of an anger and a
peevishness and a kind of reactivity
that puts some people off and also I
challenge him a little bit on he says
that ideas have people people don't have
ideas so I'd like to see him so why not
have compassion for people who have
who've been kind of taken in by this new
Marxist ideology or this relativistic
ideology it's in in some sense you can
have a lot of anger towards their kind
of professors and whatever and but
actually if if he was I think part of
the reason this is the other paradox of
Peterson he's like his message is about
transcending division talking to people
you don't agree with him coming like and
yet he is one of the most divisive
characters in society and I think part
of that is this kind of intense
reactivity to him by the dominant
culture this kind of neo Marxism this
kind of green thinking that can't
integrate what he's saying because it
can't deal with the idea of hierarchy it
can't deal with the idea of truth it
can't deal with all these things and
that's part of it for sure that's a huge
part of it but I think there is some
part where he is still in a kind of
angry reactivity to probably what
happened to him and probably kind of
that his job was at risk for like eight
months and and he was under it and he is
still under attack completely unfairly
on a regular basis but there is I wonder
if part of it is this sort of anger and
reactivity that a lot of people sense in
him that actually means that they have a
reactivity to listening to what he's
saying and and I think I think that's
the only not maybe not the only but
that's the main thing that I think his
critics have a point on although I also
think that he has he uses anger and and
in a really useful way as well and I
think a lot of people don't recognize
that like you see him revving himself up
and stay
that part of his performative aspect
he's really aligned himself he's he uses
anger as a tool like he's a he's he's
integrated in Wilbur terms and he's
integrated his red like red the kind of
anger shadow tribalism you all right
like he's integrated that in a way that
very few people in our culture have and
it's often sort of shamed and rejected
and lots of people have a problem with
anger so when they see him in that kind
of but anger if it's integrated as he
talks about like the Jungian shadow it
becomes force it becomes power it
becomes all of the stuff in the world so
I think there's a reactivity as well on
the other side so it's a complete it's a
really complex picture is really complex
yeah and I think there is AI know I
think that is a valid criticism that
I've read for many of the reasons
describing where it's you know could he
be saying yes and a bit more with the
postmodern side of it because there are
benefits there are good things and it's
good we went through a civil rights but
and all those things they're positives
so how would you some of the good things
about green I would say the good things
about green are that so I would copy
anything this postmodern kind of like
everything as a stage to develop as a
stage of development is that it takes
you out of the rigidity of the previous
stages so it allows you to start playing
yeah playing with identity playing that
the way things are done playing with
power dynamics and that playing creates
growth and it's an important stage you
know because we free ourselves from
restrictive social situations from
restrictive laws from restrictive ways
of seeing things you know I've got and
getting different perspectives from
different is a big part of it is getting
the the perspective of the underdog of
the person who's oppressed you know
which they've taken to absurd levels but
as a concept it's important to get many
voices but you also need to have a so
Francois Lyotard said that who's one of
the kind of fathers of post-modernism or
what would become post-modernism this is
very postmodern it's like oh there's no
such thing as post-modernism but he said
without the sublime which is this I this
is the point at which language fails
it's the point at which the you kind of
encounter the transcendent and you
cannot describe it is it kind of the
ineffable so without the sublime
this whole thing is doomed to madness
because you have to with all that
playing this whole relativity you like
with all of that playing that you're
doing you've got to have an anchor
you've got to have an anchor then it's
safe then it reminds me actually then
it's very psychedelic it's a you know in
the psychedelic experience it's a very
deconstructed experience extremely so
and when you have a bad trip it's when
you forget that you're tripping and you
forget that you're present you lose your
ground of being you lose your presence
and you get swept up in the the chaos
that's why they always you always tell
people in a psychedelic emergency this
will end it contextualizes that you are
having a drug experience you are having
this experience and it's going to end so
that kind of madness can can infect the
whole society as well in addition to the
films and stuff we're putting out we're
also doing events because I mean the
reason I really wanted to see Peterson
and a lot of my questions were about
integration of the shadow because what
I've done a lot of shadow work a lot of
integration work we're sort of working
with your anger working integrating all
the negative parts of yourself the the
Jungian idea of all the parts we repress
and deny and integrating them to become
most of the present in the world and
powerful and I found my life being
transformed as I've done that kind of
work like being yeah things have started
to sort of come together and I found it
really powerful and hearing him talk
about it just overlaid everything I'd
ever learned the hard way like he was
describing the process that I've been
through he was describing all of the
integration stuff so I was like wow this
the first thinker I've found to describe
this process in detail and get it
exactly right so also therefore the
focus on this message of kind of
integration also demands for me like
real-world events but we have to do the
work it's not enough just to talk about
it and it's it's invaluable to talk
about it and to do it and to kind of to
bring this knowledge out to as many
people as possible but actually to get
people give people the possibility of
doing the work themselves is the
essential part of
and therefore and this was happening in
parallel we like both of us have done
quite a lot this kind of work and we're
being mentored by a guy who's done this
work for about 40 years and where we've
been learning to lead groups ourselves
or little facilitate workshops where
people can come and just have a weekend
or a certain time to just look at what's
at their shadow look at what's really
working in their lives look at what's
holding them back and identifying that
part of themselves that wants it to
change and can make it change and then
yeah and transforming or getting a taste
of what it might be like to move past
whatever these blockages are in their
lives and and what's fascinating as well
is that this has really mapped onto the
Jordan Pederson work like it's before a
lot of this work is sort of often done
in a sort of cuts like a New Age hippie
kind of vibe of vulnerability and
sharing a truth and all this other stuff
and what Peterson does is reframes in a
much more solid way of you are coming
here to align yourself with your deeper
truth you're coming to align yourself
with the logos you are coming to
integrate your shadow and you're coming
to become more fully present to yourself
and this is the deeper story of Western
culture and that for me is is an
incredibly powerful reframing of the
kind of work we've been doing for quite
a long time absolutely yeah and it it
really speaks to the you know he talks
about this difference between rights and
responsibilities you know a law and men
really connect with that we you know I
certainly do and the ultimate person
responsibility is is over your own your
own inner house over your own being you
know it's that you do the work and you
show up as we say a lot you know you
have to show up tell the truth you know
be honest with yourself be honest with
someone else which is even more
challenging I would say but more
rewarding and also be be brave enough to
go into the places you don't want to
look at you know if that responsibly
because no one else can do that for you
so all you can really do in a workshop
is really
hold the space and guide that process to
happen but it's it's every man I'm
talking specific about the men's work
that we're doing because we there is
women's work as well but we don't run it
so you know and we connect deeply with
men's work it's that kind of personal
responsibility and then the support of
one another which is astonishing you
know it always amazes me yeah I mean we
started again I think we started this
before even I discovered you know we
started this before you can discovering
Jordan Peterson which is another kind of
uncanny synchronicity that it overlaid
on to this as we started teaching men's
work and because this is where I we see
the greatest need right now it's like
this is men as Peterson talks about are
in some sense more lost by this idea of
rights against responsibilities men have
to carry a load men have to be directed
men have to have to take on
responsibility without responsibility
we're kind of lost and I guess I kind of
knew that before and I also really
recognized in my own life as I started
working on my masculinity and working on
it with other men there's something that
we're missing a lot
this idea of vitamin M that something of
being around with other men and talking
truthfully with them and really kind of
looking at ourselves really owning our
stuff is feeding something like really
deep in us like I think and and seeing
who we are and seeing who we are in
these spaces like we would have kind of
worked together on a common project it's
like a common project we can find and do
together and this really feeds my soul
to be of all the things that we're doing
like I know all the success that we've
had so far with the films and stuff what
really feeds my soul is the workshops
and being there and hearing guys say wow
I never never felt this sense of
brotherhood before I've never I've
realized stuff about myself and had a
and a life-changing experience and this
is what's extraordinary we did the
workshop in in April and
cuz a lot of the guys have come through
the Jordan Peterson documentaries there
was a they knew the shadow they knew the
idea of aligning oneself with the truth
they were ready to go and they really
went deep and it was just or inspiring
to behold and really feels like we're on
the verge of something if we can keep
building this and people will keep
coming to the workshop I think we're on
the verge of but this this for me is the
cutting edge of where we need to go as a
culture to re-embrace I think what we've
what we've confused is the idea of we do
need to integrate both masculine and
feminine qualities within ourselves but
the way to do that is by really
connecting with our four men with our
masculinity and then we can connect with
sort of more feminine side what Jung
called the master work is integrating
the Animas of the female part of
ourselves and that comes through through
really connecting to our masculine it
gives us the grounding to then be able
to integrate the feminine and also to be
able to like meeting women for a much
more grounded place so the coming young
me in terms the inner and outer feminine
but you get a much like women can feel
that they can trust you far more when
you're really connected to your
masculine you're not you're not ashamed
of it you're not kind of sneaking around
trying to it's it's a very different
quality of presence that you bring yeah
absolutely with with women and men you
know and presence is such an important
word because true presence were you
really connected to yourself implies
that you are aligning yourself properly
because I you know having taught
meditation for years one thing I've
noticed is that there's something you
know when we're not present it's because
we don't want to be we don't really want
to be with ourselves in that moment you
know so when you come into being like
Who am I
like what am i bringing what am I
feeling what do I need to go through
that's that's the Warriors process it
really is it's a process of a kind of
inner it's a deep inner process that
requires courage and like you were
saying you know when it's happening
and on the workshops you know I've sat
in many psychedelic ceremonies and many
meditation retreats and some amazing
group work and there is just something
that happens in that space with just men
that you know we call it vitamin M
because it needs some kind of a afraid's
because it's very hard to describe in
language it's a feeling you know it's a
feeling in the air and it's one of
groundedness and it's one of support and
also for me I feel a huge amount of
relief in the whole space of like oh
it's okay to be a man okay
and when you come into that place you're
a much wiser more you know integrated
honest man and you know when men come
back to you know their partners
afterwards generally their partners see
that first off it's that kind of you
know their feeling in it and that you
know they often have good sex and why
here's well yeah so yeah it feels yeah
it feels like that's where we have to go
as a culture to me that this reom
bracing of polarity and then consciously
so it's like a paradox I think we've got
this sort of idea like the even the
Greeks talked about like this this
spiritual state of the hero's gamos the
idea is the inner marriage of the
masculine or feminine within oneself as
the higher spiritual truth and there and
I think perhaps we have some echo of
that because in our culture it's like
well then gender neutrality is is the
way to go it's like no no gender
neutrality is not the way to go the way
to go is full conscious embodiment of
the masculine for men full conscious
embodiment of the feminine for women and
then we can integrate our own in a
masculine as a woman and in a feminine
as a man and and then that's the that's
the place that we need to go and that I
think is so it's a paradox as most
things are a paradox as I also think
that the paradox of individuality and
connection is that only by truly
individuating only by truly going deeply
into ourselves and going through our
stuff can we
reach this point where we can really
meet other people and we can feel that
in some sense this sort of spiritual
truth that we are all the same person
looking at each other in some sense like
we are consciousness discovering itself
or this sort of all the hippie but
the paradox is we can only get there
through the deep work on ourselves
individually and this is something in
our workshops we talk about and it's
came to us during the last workshop it's
like we have to do it ourselves but we
don't have to do it alone
which i think is a perfect summation and
that's what we yeah that's what we
really want to give people a sense of in
the workshops
absolutely and and it's I think it's
core to everything we're doing a tribal
wisdom because you do need both you need
an intellectual framework and now you
know that's why we're going out to find
the most rebellious thinkers and that's
you know why Jordan Peterson is so
important to this as well because that
you get this framework which we didn't
have well you know we did but you know
it's much more popular now you know when
Jung was writing his books people
couldn't go on YouTube and you know look
at ours of them now people can which is
incredible so you need that but you must
also embody it if you wanted to really
change your life I think that's the
thing it's got to be lived like it's
embody means it's in your body you're
walking around with it you're feeling it
it means you're taking responsibility
for who you are all the time and you're
taking that seriously so combining the
two is is the ideal rebellious wisdom
rebellious ism